the final type of optimization for
reducing the Miss rate that we will look
at is a so-called loop interchange which
is one of the compiler optimizations
that can be done to transform the code
into code that has better locality so
suppose that we are initializing a
matrix like this by having an outer loop
and an inner loop and then we initialize
the element and then loop like this the
layout of this matrix in memory if it's
a CRA is such that it begins with a zero
zero the next element in memory will be
a zero one and so on
eventually we have the last element of
this row and only now we will have a one
zero and so on so now let's look at how
this loop accesses these elements I and
J are both zero at first so we will
access this element next J will be
incremented so we will access this
element and then this element and so on
we will access all of the rows of the
matrix before we come back and start
accessing the second element in each row
so the problem is when this is accessed
we fetched an entire cache block worth
of stuff into the cache just to use this
one element then we're going to fetch a
block here to use this one element and
by the time we reach the end of the
matrix and look back here we might have
run out of space in the cache and the
block that we would now use has been
kicked out of the cache so we fetch it
again use this one element and so on so
we have one miss per access here so a
good compiler will detect that the order
of these loops doesn't match the layout
in memory and it's going to perform what
is called a loop interchange which
amounts to simply swapping the two loops
so now the inner loop is the one that
moves to the next element in memory so
once we fetch a block from memory we end
up using the whole block only then we
move to the next block and so on once we
have done with the row we move on to the
next row so now we are nicely
sequentially accessing this may
not only does it improve locality
because now we end up accessing the
entire cache block at a time but also it
makes the access nicely sequential so
one of the pre fetchers can do a good
job on it so this works really well it
dramatically improves the hit rate that
we're getting but it is not always
possible you cannot just take any two
nested loops and transform in this way
the compiler has to prove that this code
and this code are equivalent which it
does by proving that there are no
dependencies between iterations of these
loops